Speaker: When you’re having a drink together on a lazy Sunday afternoon,
it seems like such a good idea. You’re the best of friends,
you get on well, what could be better than going on holiday together?
Well, before you get carried away and log on to Tripadvisor,
let me give you one word of advice.
Don’t.
Holidays together are never a good idea.
Believe me, I know. I’ve been there.
And I have a trail of broken friendships to prove it.
Because, no matter how well you think you know your friends,
you don’t really know them until you’ve lived under the same roof for a week.
That’s roughly how long it takes to discover that
your caring friend is really a hypochondriac control freak.
One of the biggest problems with going on holiday with friends
is the difference in expectations.
You’re looking forward to relaxing on the beach with Joanna Trollope’s latest must-read novel,
while their mission is to visit every ancient ruin within a 50-mile radius.
Which is all fine if they don’t mind going it alone,
but when they try to make you feel guilty for lying on your lounger, it’s a different story.
A few years ago,
we hired a motorhome on the west coast of Canada with another couple.
Now, I’m not really a camping kind of girl,
but since this motorhome was like the Waldorf on wheels,
and North American campsites are known for all their mod cons,
I thought that I’d be pretty safe.
Unfortunately, what we didn’t realize is that
our friends had decided this would be the ideal opportunity to get back to nature.
They had booked the ultimate get-away-from-it-all campsite, high in the mountains.
Not only were we getting away from civilization,
we were also getting away from electricity, running water,
and anything else that made life tolerable.
Our friends sulked when I suggested that maybe we could compromise
and move on to a different campsite for the second half of the holiday.
‘So, you want to give up all this fantastic scenery for a proper toilet?’ they sneered.
Well, yes, that’s exactly what I wanted.
Because, I have to tell you,
no amount of spectacular scenery makes up for a smelly hole in the ground
next to a sign saying ‘Beware of the Bears’.
But if there’s one thing guaranteed to bring on a major holiday fall-out, it’s children.
Your own can be bad enough,
but a week with someone else’s hyperactive toddler is enough to turn
even the most mild-mannered of us into Supernanny.
And you try packing your own children off to bed at a reasonable hour
when theirs are still bouncing off the ceiling at midnight,
hyped up on fizzy drinks and video games!
We knew our friends Amanda and Simon took a relaxed attitude towards parenting,
but we didn’t realize just how relaxed
until we shared a villa in Spain with them and their ten-year-old son.
‘Freddie has never heard the word “No” – it stifles his creativity,’
they boasted to us proudly, as he hurled himself fully clothed into the swimming pool,
five minutes before we were due to go out to dinner.
He certainly heard it that holiday,
bellowed by my husband
after Freddie tried to fire a catapult into our daughter’s face at point-blank range.
He heard a few other choice words, too.
Ten years on, I think Amanda and her husband still blame us for the fact that
Freddie isn’t a concert pianist.
It’s even worse when one of you has children and the other doesn’t.
I once spent a week in France, breastfeeding my newborn daughter in a wardrobe
because our child-free friends hadn’t allowed for the vast amount of baggage a baby comes with
and had allocated us the smallest room.
And they were most put out that we couldn’t drop everything
and hit the town at night, like in the old days.
But how things change!
A few years later, we went on holiday with the same friends,
now proud parents themselves,
and we weren’t allowed to speak above a whisper for ten days.
So, if it’s such a bad idea, why do I keep going back for more?
It may be because holidays with friends are like childbirth:
after a while, you forget the pain and it seems like a good idea to have another go.
Which reminds me,
my sister and her husband have just invited us to join them on a mini-break to Barcelona.
Now, honestly, what could be nicer than a family get-together?